now we can talk about creatin
monohydrate you're probably sick of
hearing me talk about it cuz I've been
doing it for so many years but it's for
good reason there's so much data on it
it is by far the most widely studied
sport supplement and it's not even close
it's been studied in every
population healthy diseased young old
men women kids so on and so forth and
there's really very limited side effects
if any that have been reported now
creatine itself is a naturally occurring
derivative of three very specific amino
acids methine Glycine and Arginine these
are really really common uh creatine
itself I typically have talked about how
it's stored in muscle and used as a
great fuel source but many people don't
realize it's actually also stored in
your liver testes and brain the last one
of course is where we're going to pay
our attention to today now it's stored
in the brain so that it can be used as a
very quick fuel source your gear should
be turning at this point remember one of
the primary issues we have with the TBS
is that energy demand problem and so it
made a ton of sense to scientists very
early on to say okay we know that we
have energy issues we know that the
fastest way any of our tissues can make
energy is through monohydrate and
we know it's in stored in the brain
already it makes sense to try that to
both prevent reduce the risk of and then
treat brain injuries so it's no surprise
when we look at the research here on
both TBI as well as aging and normal
brain health research to find that
monohydrate often improves
cognitive function in both brain injury
and normal healthy aging folks now it's
not the world's most powerful neut
Tropic but it is effective and been
shown again in many models and many
studies across many Laboratories so
because it's so effective at giving
energy especially in low oxygen
situations you'll see evidence across
injury and TBI papers but also just
normal cognitive function and healthy
individuals uh to see benefit right so
is effective in all of those
populations and the physiology
biochemistry make total sense now
specifically regarding tbis and
concussions one of the things you want
to pay attention to a lot is What's
called the second impact
syndrome many people have not heard of
this but this is the basic idea of
repeated head blows cause more
damage as time goes on and so one of the
things that's been shown with creatine
is it is really effective for that
second impact syndrome more specifically
it's been shown that the repeated head
blows cause more damage if the creatine
is depleted prior to the additional
impacts okay so imagine you had an one
single impact the more creatine
depletion you have the worst damage you
get if you have a secondary
impact this is any athlete that's going
to be in sparring or competitions where
we're getting a lot of impacts this is
military or special forces or anything
like that that is again is getting low
impact repeated exposures or blasts okay
the more creatine depletion that happens
the worse the damage in your brain that
occurs after the second or repeated
impact so right there we can see that if
you've had an injury making sure your
creatine stores are replenished as
quickly as possible is really important
if we're going to continue in that
exposure now that's important because
many people don't re recognize or
realize the first injury happened to
begin with
okay most of them are underreported most
don't realize it hard to diagnose and so
prophylactically it just maybe makes
some sense to make sure that you're
taking care of business not necessarily
just when you have an injury but if you
even think you're at risk or in
high-risk situations or prior to
high-risk exposures or or
competitions right good example of this
there's a pretty famous study I think it
was in high school football players high
school or college but nonetheless
football players American football that
is um that did indicate the Crea stores
in their brain I think specifically in
the motor and prefrontal cortex reduced
over the course of the season now this
is not a perfect study design but you
can see what this is alluding to if
you're in a situation again with
repeated him head impacts over the
course of a season the number of impacts
in fact maybe I'll back up quickly in
this particular study what they did is
they filmed the games and so what they
they measured is for each individual
player how many head contacts they had
but there was an association between
those players that had more head impacts
not even necessarily injuries and the
level of creatin reduction in the brain
over the course of the season so again
we're making some assumptions here but I
think it's fair to at least say it's
plausible the more impacts on your brain
the more creatine is reduced potentially
the higher risk you are for second
impact syndrome injuries now before we
go any further with the creatine
research
I need to do a quick pause and explain
to you what I mean when I say strong
evidence or weak evidence there's no
perfect way to do that but an easy way
to roughly understand is called the
strength of evidence scale okay so I
will abbreviate that in the rest of
today's episode by just calling it the S
OE the strength of evidence okay this
takes into account research design the
quality of the relevant studies the
applicability to Patient Care and a
number of other factors it's to you
ultimately to decide what is an
actionable level of evidence or not some
people that are maybe suffering from a
brain injury consider a study in animals
to be enough and others want to see a
randomized control trial in humans
that's not for me to decide that's up to
you but I do want to share with you
where the level of evidence is and you
can make your choice from there so the S
OE is on a scale of 1 to five a score of
one is the best that is the highest
score possible this means we see
consistent results across multiple
studies we've seen it in both randomized
control trials as well as systematic
reviews and so on and so forth a score
of say four or five would be the
opposite that would be our lowest score
maybe there's evidence there but it's
from case studies or case control
studies maybe it's mechanism only or
some other model that's close maybe
research from aging or dementia not the
same as brain injury but it shares some
mechanisms you get the idea here so for
example the soe for crean monohydrate is
a two my opinion personally that's
pretty good summarizing the collective
evidence here there's been a lot of
research on everything from kids to
rugby players to mountain bikers and
collectively you're going to see it
supports cognitive Health it's been
shown actually in psychiatric disorders
there's I believe two randomized control
trials that I'm aware of that have found
five grams of creatine per day added in
addition to anti-depressant treatments
improved depressive symptoms right so
take that for what you will and
regarding TBI and brain injuries there's
an argument we can make here for
preventative use specifically for
neuronal damage and injury there's been
shown to reduce cortical damage
following a TBI by anywhere between 35
to
50% that'd be 5 pretty substantial
amount there should catch your
attention they don't know exactly how it
works works but it's thought to prevent
some of that mitochondrial dysfunction I
was talking about a few minutes ago uh
helps maintain the membrane
Health certainly has a role in fending
off that downstream ractive oxygen
species ATP calcium so a lot of those
things we just got done covering that's
why we covered them creatin probably has
a role again we need more information
here but likely has a role in in either
eliminating or at least drastically
reducing some of those issues and
finally then what you care more about is
the downstream TBI effects have also
been documented what I mean here is
sleep cognition and actual mood seem to
be enhanced with the creatine
furthermore there's actually some
studies that specifically been done on
kids there's one I'm thinking of in
detail here that was everything from 1
to 18y olds that had severe TB in this
particular paper they gave them 0.4 G
per kilogram of body weight if you do
the math that ends up being a a pretty
standard dose but appropriately it was
done based on body size you have 2year
olds and 18y olds we can't give them all
just five grams so a relative dose was
given to them within 4 hours post injury
and done so for 6 months in that
particular study they found improvements
in everything from Amnesia to the length
of stay in the ICU improvements in
communication Locomotion and social
skills and more importantly what I one
of the things I loved most about this
was this the researchers were clear in
the fact that the treatment provided
cost significantly less than the
standard treatment protocol and this is
something I thought was really important
because I know supplements are not cheap
and many of you can't afford any cost
whatsoever but if you can while creatine
I know I know I hear this all the time
has gotten more expensive in re recent
years it's still likely far cheaper than
a standard Hospital protocol so if you
can possibly afford it
seems to be a pretty good option another
thing I want to point out here because
it comes up all the time as well in this
study again remember kids six months of
creatine there were no signs of any
kidney liver or heart side effects so
overall we would deem creatine as a
pretty strong chance of success in both
the physiology as well as actual
symptoms with a very low likelihood of
injury or adverse effects for me
personally I wouldn't hesitate to give
this to one of my kids if they have it
it's entirely up to you to make your
choice I'm not advocating you do
anything you don't want to do or
uncomfortable with just letting you know
for me when I look at the research as a
parent myself of two young kids I I
would not hesitate at all to use this in
my children so how do you actually use
creatine well you have a couple of
options one you can try to get this from
Whole Foods and I'll present to you
exactly what that would mean in amounts
or you can use the supplementation route
I guess a third option would be to use a
combination of both so most of the data
on monohydrate for brain injuries
they're typically using dosages of about
20 gram per day now that's four times
the typical dose you'll see for
performance benefits so this is one of
our major things we have to pay
attention to this is not a dosage that's
just your standard five grams five grams
five grams it is much higher for the the
brain health benefits now often times
that's a little bit challenging and so
you'll see typical protocols instead of
taking 20 GRS at once are things like 5
G administered four times per day right
so the the benefits are typically
thought of as both acute and chronic I
know I have said many many many years
now that a is not an acute thing
it's not caffeine you don't take
creatine right now and feel this big
stimulation effects it takes weeks or
months to build up
however one paper that came out recently
kind of shook everyone's World a 2024
paper get just one paper here so temper
a little bit I'm tempering my own
expectations but a recent paper
suggested that a very high dose I think
it was
35 grams per kilogram of body weight was
enough to attenuate the drop in
cognitive performance after sleep
deprivation so you take people through
sleep deprivation the next day you give
them this giant bullet of and
those that took the had less of a
cognitive drop from sleep deprivation I
actually think the benefits started at
about 3 and 1 half hours and lasted up
to 9 hours so potentially say something
bad happened and you didn't get a great
night of sleep you could take this maybe
20 gram dose in the morning and by noon
or so or for the rest of the day you
might have some improvements in
cognitive function that's the first
paper I've ever seen that I'm aware of
to show an acute effect of creatine but
since that was so dramatic I wanted to
make sure I drew it to your attention so
to me you have an option there for brain
health and now if we consider this in
context of the episode of today even
getting this in immediately
potentially has a brain impact and
that's why I wanted to bring that study
up as it relates to the current topic
other Studies have found that that 20
grams per day for seven days enhances
cognitive function um this is
specifically the mountain biker study
I'm referring to and so generally me
personally this is not the studies this
is me personally based on the work that
I've read I think 5 to 10 grams per day
is probably plenty for most people as a
prophylactic so kind of an ongoing
option to be at that number that said
and again candidly this is what I do for
my athletes seven days or so prior to a
high-risk situation a competition
something like that a race or an event
we're going to up that dose to 20 to 30
grams for that seven days all right
again one more time when I do that it is
hard to choke down 20 grams at once
that's a handful of scoops and so we
will often try to get 5 to 10 grams in
the morning 5 to 10 grams at night and
split up the dosages throughout the day
simply from my practical perspective now
one of my favorite sayings is there are
no free passes in physiology creatine is
not perfect it's not a Panacea and there
are some potential risks the biggest one
is GI distress some people have a gas or
bloting
or stomach cramps at even 5 grams a day
so taking them to 20 or 30 may cause
some serious issues it's not that
frequently reported I've never
experienced it I can't think of a
situation where I've ever had an athlete
or client reported but it is a real
thing it is pretty uncommon but is
reported and so you will want to pay
attention to that outside of that there
isn't really any documented problems
associated even with high dosages 20
plus grams a day for years there have
been studies in kids elderly various
what we call risky or unhealthy
populations for many many
years you can St look across basic all
those studies and you just won't find
really any other Adverse Events outside
of the possible mild or moderate GI
distress now if the supplement does give
you GI distress or you can't afford it
don't have access to it or for any other
reason just don't like supplements you
can theoretically get here with food but
it is admittedly very challenging
especially for those vegans and
vegetarians because the primary source
of from food comes from muscle or
meat the most common places of
and meat are going to be things like
beef chicken salmon tuna Cod and they
mostly have somewhere between 400 to 600
milligrams of creatine per 100 G of meat
now I know in America you're thinking
what the hell is 100 G the rest of the
world knows exactly what that means but
100 gr is about 3 and2 oun okay a
typical serving size at a restaurant is
you know 7 oun or so and so you can kind
of double it in other words beef
specifically has 600 milligrams of
creatine per 100 grams but a typical
serving is 200 g so you'd be getting
12200 migr 1200 milligram is also 1.2 G
okay now the average American at least
eats about 350 gram or 12 ounces of meat
per day so if you did some basic math
there which would mean you're at about
2,000 milligrams or 2 grams of creatine
per day so while it is possible
theoretically to get all your creatine
from food it's honestly quite
challenging so supplementation just
might be the better option in this case
if you enjoyed this clip you can watch
the full episode Episode by clicking
here